<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The merchant royall A sermon preached at White-Hall before the Kings Maiestie, at the nuptials of the Right Honourable the Lord Hay and his Lady, vpon the Twelfe day last being Ianuar. 6. 1607.</title>
            <author>Wilkinson, Robert, Dr. in Divinity.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73427</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25658.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S123341</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900605</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900605</idno>
            <idno type="VID">133105</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73427)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 133105)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2088:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The merchant royall A sermon preached at White-Hall before the Kings Maiestie, at the nuptials of the Right Honourable the Lord Hay and his Lady, vpon the Twelfe day last being Ianuar. 6. 1607.</title>
                  <author>Wilkinson, Robert, Dr. in Divinity.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Felix Kyngston for Iohn Flasket, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the black Beare,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Robert Wilkinson.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>In this edition p. 2 line 1 has "dignitie"; line 2 has "holie". Quire A is in the same setting as the other two 1607 London editions.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Carlisle, James Hay, --  Earl of, 1580-1636 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Carlisle, Honora Hay, --  Countess of, d. 1614 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Wives --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:133105:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133105:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE MERCHANT ROYALL. A SERMON PREACHED AT White-Hall before the Kings Maieſtie, at the Nuptials of the Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable the Lord HAY and his Lady, vpon the Twelfe day laſt being <hi>lanuar. 6. 1607.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>sailing ship and two devices or crests above it described in McKerrow, pp. 137-38, at device no. 356: at left, "a garb, or wheatsheaf, on a wreath" (perhaps the crest of the Lord Hay?); at right, the crest of the Denny family (Honora Denny being the Lady referred to in the book title)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by FELIX KYNGSTON for <hi>John Flasket,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſigne of the black Beare. 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:133105:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133105:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE THE LORD HAY, AND TO HIS late eſpouſed the Lady HONORIA; the Author hereof wiſheth all conſolation in Chriſt, continuall comfort in mariage, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with a conſcionable obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance of the contents of this Sermon.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>LOE here (Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) preſented into your hands what lately ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in your eares. A ſhip firſt built in Paradiſe and for the pleaſure of the land, but ſince repaired for the Merchants vſe against the troubles of the ſea: which ſince I am enioyned to launch out into the maine, and to make publique both beyond the merit of the</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:133105:3"/> 
               <hi>thing, and alſo beyond mine owne meaning, I could finde none more fit <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto whom to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate it now in the print, than your Honorable ſelues, for whoſe ſake it was firſt preached. I hope I ſhall neuer make it the laſt end of my La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, to pleaſe man; yet I finde in this, that I haue pleaſed ſome and diſpleaſed other: but why ſhould I looke to pleaſe all, whereas God himſelfe hath ſo ſeldome done it? Therefore they which thinke me too bitter, must yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that I bite nothing but ſinne; and what reaſon is there to fauour ſinne, through occaſion where of the world was drowned to puniſh it, the Law was ordained to preuent it, the Sonne of the highest died to ſatisfie for it, and the world againe must be destroyed to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh it? Yea what reaſon is there to fauour any ſinne, whereas there is no one which fauoureth <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, but all imperilling <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s in the hope of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, as</hi> Eue <hi>by her eating <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndermined</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam. <hi>They againe which thinke that ſinne ſhould not be derided or corrected in this kind, must alſo conſider that euery ſin is to be taxed in his proper kinde; as in the Scripture ſins ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring of error are refelled with arguments,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:133105:3"/> 
               <hi>and ſuch as bee foule and hainous are beaten do wne with iudgements, but thoſe which were ridiculous were indeede derided, as</hi> Elias <hi>the Prophet ſported at the Prieſts of Baal, and</hi> Iob <hi>at his fooliſh comforters. Yea and how plaies</hi> Eſay <hi>with the wanton gestures of women,</hi> ſtretching out their neckes, minſing and tinckling with their feete, &amp;c. Chap. 3. 16. <hi>But</hi> Moſes <hi>more with the nicenes of women,</hi> Too daintie to venture <hi>(not their knees in deuotion) but</hi> the ſoles of their feete vpon the ground, Deut. 28. 56. <hi>no doubt a ſore ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture. But nothing ſo taunting as that in</hi> Salomon, <hi>where the whore is mockt for a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie, and ſhe that offered her ſelfe to other mens lust, yet is ſet our for a Saint with offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of peace to God,</hi> Prou. 7. 14. <hi>I hope ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all good people will priuiledge me by theſe holie preſidents; yea I am ſure of this that none will finde fault with me, but ſuch as first finde a fault in themſelues, and to ſuch I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe my ſelfe indeede a Preacher, and to haue preached all this for them, as Chriſt in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell profeſſed of himſelfe, that</hi> he came to call
<pb facs="tcp:133105:4"/> ſinners. <hi>And thus in my most true and ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt loue I commend you in the midſt of your mariage ioyes to that joy and peace which is in God.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours in all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian deuotion, Robert Wilkinſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:133105:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED AT WHITE HALL, VPON THE SIXTH of <hi>Ianuary 1607.</hi> being Twelfe day: At the Nuptials of the Right Honorable the Lord <hi>HAY</hi> and his Lady.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PROV. 31. 14.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>She is like a Merchants ſhip, ſhe bringeth her foode from a farre.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Scripture, and in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect this whole chapter is a Scripture written for women; and more peculiarly a Scripture writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in praiſe of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; yet not gloſingly to make them bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than they be, but ſoberly and truly to ſhew the what they ſhould be; A ſcripture Wherein as in a glaſſe are ſet out to our view all the perfections and ornaments,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:133105:5"/> all the dignitie, beautie, dutie of a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous wife and holie woman. The diuell at the firſt began his temptation by prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the woman, by telling her, that if ſhe knew her ſelfe, ſhe wanted but one thing to make her like God; And from the diuel (I think) it comes, that ſo many men ſince, in euery age, haue ſo wantonly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed their time, their wits, their pennes, and ſometime their penſils too, either vainely to magnifie, or vily to embaſe the dignitie of women; the cauſes of which follie I take to be theſe, either for that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally they did not know them, and then they wrote fooliſhly, or for that ſomtime they doted on them, and then they prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed immoderatly, or elſe for that ſometime they hated them, and then they railed fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſlie: But there are, to ratifie the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent diſcourſe and praiſe of women, three things, firſt God, by whoſe ſprit it was conceiued: ſecondly <hi>Bathſheba</hi> a woman, by whoſe mouth it was taught: thirdlie, <hi>Salomon</hi> a man, yea the wiſeſt of men, by whoſe pen it was endited, that is to ſay, God in ſpired it into the mother, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:133105:5"/> taught it to <hi>Salomon</hi> her ſonne, and then <hi>Salomon</hi> her ſonne publiſht it to the world: therfore if we ſpeak of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of a good woman, who knoweth her better than ſhe her ſelfe? who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth her better than man that liueth with her? yea who knoweth her ſo well as God that made her? Againe, if in this deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion any thing might ſeeme too much in praiſe, it was not a woman, but a man that wrote it; if any thing might ſeeme too grieuous or burdenſome in precept, it was not a man, but a woman that impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it; or if any thing might ſeeme either too much, or too little, or other wiſe than it ſhould be, it was neither man nor wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, but God that firſt directed it: and thus in one deſcription of a vertuous wife and holy woman (which is not any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther author, nor yet elſewhere in any part of Scripture) wee haue a man, a woman, yea God himſelf, and al out of one mouth ſpeaking and conſpiring; She that hath cares to hearelet her heare.</p>
            <p>In the tenth verſe of this Chapter, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> makes proclamation, <hi>VVho ſhall</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:133105:6"/> 
               <hi>finde a vertuous woman?</hi> which yet impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not (as S. <hi>Augustine</hi> noteth) <hi>Inuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di impoſſibilitatem, ſed difficultatem,</hi> Not as if to finde a vertuous woman were a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of impoſſibilitie, but yet for all that, a thing of ſome difficultie; and therfore he crieth her with her marks; <hi>She will doe her huſband good, and not euill; She riſeth while it is yet night; She putteth her hands to the wheele; She ſtretcheth out her hands to the poore; She openeth her mouth with wiſedome,</hi> &amp;c. Thus ſhewing ſometime what ſhee doth, ſometime what ſhe is, ſometime what ſhe is worth, and ſomtime what ſhe is like, as here; <hi>She is like a ſhip,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>She is indeed, and yet ſhe ſcarſe is, and therefore becauſe ſhe is ſo ſearſe, it was needfull to ſhew, not only what ſhe is, but alſo what ſhe is like too; for how ſhall he finde her, that neuer ſaw her, that neuer had her, that ſcarſe heard of her, how ſhall he find her, but by ſome ſenſible re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of her? and therefore as <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic. s.</hi> when the Church cried her husband, (<hi>I charge you, O daughters of Jeruſalem, if you finde my welbeloued, &amp;c.</hi>) ſhe deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:133105:6"/> him by reſemblance: <hi>My welbeloued is white and ruddie, the chiefest of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, his head is like a gold, his eyes like doues, his cheekes like a bed of ſpices, his lippes like lilies, his legges like pillers of marble,</hi> euerie thing was like ſomething; ſo of the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous woman it is ſaid heere, that ſhe is like a ſhippe; and <hi>Prou. 12.</hi> ſhe is like a crowne, and in the Canticles ſometime like a Roſe, ſometime like a Lilie, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time like a garden of flowers, ſometime like a ſpring of waters: In a word, ſhe is like to many things, but as it is ſaid verſ. 10. <hi>Pearles and precious ſtones are not like to her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>She is like a ſhip</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) and it may well be, for the world is like the Sea: for ſo ſaith S. <hi>John, Before the throne there was a ſea of glaſſe,</hi> Reuel. 4. and that was the world, tranſitorie and brittle as glaſſe, tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous and troubleſome like the ſea, wherein as the wind raiſeth vp the waues, and one waue wallowes in the necke of another, ſo this troubleſome life of ours begins in weeping, goes on in ſorrow, and the ende of one woe is but the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:133105:7"/> of another. O what time might a man aske to ſet downe all the miſeries of this life! the feare, the care, the anguiſh that daily accompanieth the bodie and ſoule of man; the labours &amp; ſorowes cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, the cauſualties vncertaine, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions and vnquietnes of them that liue among vs, ſharpe aſſaults and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of them that hate vs, but chiefly the vnfaithfulnes and treacherie of them that ſeeme to loue vs: againſt theſe ſtormes to ſaue men from drowning did God ordaine the woman, as a ſhip vpon the ſea, that as <hi>Noah</hi> made an Arke, and by that Arke eſcaped the flood; ſo man by marrying with the woman might paſſe thorough all the labours of this life, vnto which doubtleſſe God had reſpect when he ſaid, <hi>It is not good for man to bee alone, let <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s make him a helpe meete for him;</hi> as much as to ſay, a ſhip to ſaue him, therefore he which hath no wife may ſeeme to be like <hi>Jonas</hi> in the ſea, left in the midſt of a miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable world to ſinke or ſwim, or ſhift for himſelfe; but then comes a wife like a ſhip and waſts him home: but ye muſt ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:133105:7"/> that <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaketh here of a good wife, as verſ. 10. <hi>VVho ſhall finde a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertuous woman?</hi> For otherwiſe if ſhee which was made to comfort in euerie ſtorme be ſtormie and troubleſome her ſelfe, then is ſhe not like a Ship, but like the ſea, and then to bee ſo ſhipt, it were better with <hi>Ionas</hi> to be caſt into the ſea.</p>
            <p>But if ſhe be good, ſhe is like a Ship in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and to nothing ſo like as to a Ship; for ſhe ſits at the ſterne, and by diſcretion as by Card and Compaſſe ſhapes her courſe; her countenance and conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are ballaſed with ſobernes and graui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; her ſailes are full of winde, as if ſome wiſedome from aboue had inſpired or blowne vpon her; ſhee ſtandeth in the ſhrowdes, and caſteth out her leade, and when ſhe hath ſounded, ſhe telleth (as <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chol</hi> did to <hi>Dauid</hi>) of depth and danger. <note place="margin">1. Sam. 19. 11.</note> If by default ſhe be grounded, ſhe caſteth out her ankers (as <hi>Rahab</hi> did) and by win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <note place="margin">Joſhua 2. 21.</note> of her ſelfe, ſhe gets afloate againe. If ſhe ſpie within her kenning, any trouble to bee nigh, either ſhe makes forward, if ſhe finde her ſelfe able, or elſe with <hi>Pilats</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 27. 19.</note>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:133105:8"/> wife ſhe ſets ſaile away; She commands, and countermaunds each man to his charge, ſome to their tackling, ſome to the maſt, ſome to the maine top, as if ſhe, and none but ſhe were Captaine, Owner, Maſter of the ſhip; and yet ſhe is not Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, but the Maſters mate; a royall Ship ſhe is, for the King himſelfe takes pleaſure in her beautie, <hi>Pſal. 4s.</hi> and if ſhee bee a Merchantstoo, then is ſhe the Merchant royall.</p>
            <p>Againe, as ſhe is like a ſhip, conſidered in her ſelf, and in her proper vertues, ſo is ſhe likewife, being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared with her ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner too: She is like a Ship indeed, for firſt who ſoeuer marries, ventures; he ventures his eſtate, hee ventures his peace, he ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures his libertie, yea many men by mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage aduenture their ſoules too: for which cauſe the Iſraelites were forbidden to match their daughters with the Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites, leſt they ſhould turne them from God, to ſerue other gods, <hi>Deut. 7.</hi> which <hi>Salomon</hi> notwithſtanding did, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made (as ſome men thought) a ſhrewd aduenture of his ſoule. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:133105:8"/> (euen to preuent too much aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture likewiſe) is marriage compared to a ſhip, which of all artificiall creatures, is the moſt deliberatiue, for ſhe ſailes not, but by ſounding, leſt by her vnheedines ſhe runne her ſelfe aground: In like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, neither man nor woman will at any time (if they bee wiſe) reſolue either of mariage, or of any thing in mariage, but vpon the weightieſt deliberation. He is ſet out for the image of a foole that ſaid, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>illam emi, &amp;c. I haue bought a farme, and I</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 14. 18.</note> 
               <hi>must needes goe out to ſee it,</hi> for hee ſhould haue ſeene it firſt and bought it after; as it is ſaid of the vertuous woman here, <hi>She conſidereth a field and gets it,</hi> verſ. 16. that is, ſhe thinkes of it firſt, and makes her pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe after; and when either man or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man forget this in mariage, they purchaſe ioy enough for the day of their mariage, and repentance enough for all the time after. It is ſaid of <hi>Jepthaes daughter,</hi> Iudg. 11. that <hi>ſhe went out to bewaile the daies of her virginitie;</hi> but in truth many mens daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters may goe out to bewaile the daies of their mariage, yea and many men too
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:133105:9"/> looke back to the ſingle life, as the Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians in the red ſea looked backe to the land; <note place="margin">Exod. 14.</note> and ſo they are puniſht with late re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, like thoſe fooliſh mariners Act. 27. who, becauſe they tooke not counſell in the hauen, were forced to aduiſe vpon a wracke: and what is the cauſe of this? lack of forecaſt, becauſe they ſound not firſt whether it bee fit to marrie, or yet to marrie, or whether he bee fit, or ſhe be fit, fit in degree, in diſpoſition, in religion: and therefore as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith of vowing, ſo ſay we of marrying, <hi>Be not raſh with thy mouth;</hi> but ſound firſt and ſaile after, that is, deliberate firſt, and marrie after.</p>
            <p>Again, ſhe is like a ſhip for her vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall vſe: A houſe is indeed to dwell in, but not to trauaile in, but a ſhippe is both to trauaile in, and as it were to dwell in too, to eate, and drink, and ſleepe, and labour, and meditate, and pray too; as if to bee in a ſhip were to be in another earth, the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-world: In like manner a man hath a friend for pleaſure, a ſeruant for profit, and ſor vſes to Godward a ſpirituall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructor too, but a wife ſerues for al theſe,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:133105:9"/> that is, for pleaſure, for profit, and (if ſhe be good) to bring her husband to good too.</p>
            <p>Againe, of all theſe ſame <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tenſilia,</hi> (I meane of moueable inſtruments) a ſhip is the hugeſt and the greateſt, and yet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded (as ye ſee) by the helme or ſterne, a ſmall peece of wood; ſo ought the wife (though a great comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der in the houſe) yet to be turned and ruled by a word of her husband. <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith not, ſhe is like a houſe (as many women be, as good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue a houſe as to diſſwade or weane them from their wils) but like a ſhip; not like <hi>Vaſhti</hi> the wife of <hi>Aſſuerus,</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all the power of the kingdome could not moue to come to her husband, no not to the King himſelfe, <hi>Ester</hi> 1. but ſhe muſt follow her husband, as the Iſraelites followed the clowdie piller in the wildernes, which <note place="margin">Numb. 9.</note> when it ſtood, they ſtaied, and when it went they followed, and ſo muſt ſhe.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, leſt any man doate too much vpon this heauenly ſhip of earthly ioyes, we muſt remember, that as a ſhip is not a place of continuall habitation, but onely
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:133105:10"/> for paſſage, ſo is the ſocietie of the wife, though comfortable and ioyfull for the time, yet laſting only for a time, a help to hold him vp &amp; comfort him, during this tranſitory, ſhort, and troubleſome pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage; but the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is another, a happier, a more laſting mariage with the Lambe, which neither departure, diuorce, nor death can ſeparate, and for this wee muſt forſake father, mother, wife, children, goods, lands, &amp;c. for this the liuing muſt renounce his life, the King muſt leaue his crowne, the Bridegrome muſt leaue his Bride, and the Bride muſt leaue her bed, becauſe for this the Saints doe crie, <hi>Come Lord Jeſus, come quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as the ſaying is in the ſchooles, <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudo non currit quatuor pedibus:</hi> Many things may be like, yet nothing like in all things. Therfore though a woman in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things be like a ſhip, yet in ſome things ſhe muſt be vnlike, and ſome qualities of a ſhip ſhe muſt not haue: As for example, one ſhip may belong to many Mercha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, and one Merchant may be owner in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhips; yet neither may one woman di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:133105:10"/> her loue to many men, nor one man diuide himſelfe to many women, therfore <hi>Lamech</hi> ſpake with great incongruitie, yea it was like falſe Latin when he ſaid, <hi>Heare yee wiues of Lamech,</hi> Geneſ 4. 23. for wiues admitno pluralitie when they bee conſtrued with one husband, becauſe (as the Prophet ſaith) though God at the firſt <hi>had abundance of ſpirit, yet he made but one;</hi> Mal. 2. but one woman of one rib, for the helpe and comfort of one man.</p>
            <p>Secondly, of all the goods which men poſſeſſe, onely a ſhip cannot be houſed: a man hath a ſhop for his wares, a barne for his corne, a cheſt for his mony, &amp; a houſe wherein to hide his head, but no caſe to couer a ſhip; but ſo muſt not a vertuous woman bee, for it is a note of the vnchaſt woman, that her <hi>feete cannot abide in her houſe,</hi> but <hi>now ſhe is without, now in the ſtreet, and lies in waite at euery corner,</hi> Prou. 7. 11. 12. So as who ſo ſeeth her ſeeth her al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies gadding, that hee may ſalute her, as men ſalute at ſea, Whither are ye bound? But <hi>Rachel</hi> and <hi>Leach</hi> are noted to bee in the houſe while <hi>Iacob</hi> was abroad in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:133105:11"/> field, Geneſ. 31. onely <hi>Dinah</hi> was a ſtrag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and ſet vp ſaile to Shichem, but ſhe came home with ſhame, and made an ill voiage.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, a ſhip of all things is moue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and carried with the winde; but ſo muſt not a good woman be, for of the ill woman it is ſaid, Prouerbs <hi>5. Herpaths are moueable, thou canſt not know them:</hi> She is inconſtant, light headed, and vaine, now ſhe loues, anon ſhe hates, now ſhe obeies, anon ſhe rebels; gentle and Kinde to day, crooked and vnkinde to morrow; for ſhe ſailes but by guſts, that all her goodneſſe takes her by fits, like the good daies of an ague: and whereas <hi>Ruth</hi> ſhewed more <note place="margin">Ruth 3.</note> goodnes at her latter end than at her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, an ill wiſe ſhe weth more good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in one day of her beginning, than in ſeuen yeeres of her latter end: therefore ſuch muſt remember what <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith of the good woman here, ſhe <hi>girdeth her loynes with ſlrength,</hi> that is, her minde with ſtaiednes and conſtancie, ver. 17. and verſ. 12. more plainely, <hi>She Will doe her huſband good, and not euill, all the daies of her life,</hi> that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:133105:11"/> is, ſhe is as obedient and tractable after twentie yeeres triall, as at the day of her marriage.</p>
            <p>But of all qualities a woman muſt not haue one quality of a ſhip, and that is, too much rigging. Oh what a wonder it is to ſee a ſhip vnder ſaile, with her tacklings, and her maſts, and her tops, and top gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants, with her vpper deckes, and her ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deckes, and ſo bedeckt; with her ſtreames, flagges, and enſignes, and I know not what; yea but a world of wonders it is to ſee a woman created in Gods image ſo miſcreate oft times &amp; deformed, with her French, her Spaniſh, and her fooliſh faſhions, that he that made her when hee lookes vpon her ſhall hardlie Know her, with her plumes, her fannes, and a ſilken vizard, with a ruffe like a ſaile, yea a ruffe like a rainebow, with a feather in her cap like a flag in her top, to tell (I think) which way the winde will blow. <hi>Eſay</hi> made a proffer in the third of his prophecie to ſet out by enumeration the ſhop of theſe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, Their bonnets, and their bracelets, and their tablets, their ſlippers, and their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:133105:12"/> mufflers, their vailes, their wimples, and their criſping pinnes; of ſome where of if one ſhould ſay to me as <hi>Philip</hi> ſometime ſaid to the Eunuch, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandest thou What thou readest?</hi> Act. 8. I might anſwere with the Eunuch againe, <hi>How can I with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a guide?</hi> that is, vnleſſc ſome Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman would comment on the text. But <hi>Eſay</hi> was then, and we are now; now that fancy hath multiplied the text of faſhions with the time; ſo as what was then but a ſhop, is now increaſed to a ſhip of vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. But what ſaith the Scripture? <hi>The Kings daughter is all glorious within,</hi> Pſal. 45. and as ſhips which are the faireſt in ſhew, yet are not alwaies the fitteſt for vſe; ſo neither are women the more to be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, but the more to bee ſuſpected for their faire trappings. Yet wee condemne not in greater perſonages the vſe of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments; yea wee teach that ſiluer, ſilkes, and gold were created not only for the neceſſity, but alſo for the ornament of the Saints, in the practiſe where of <hi>Rebeccah</hi> a holy woman is noted to haue receiued from <hi>Jſaac</hi> a holy man euen earings, abil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:133105:12"/> and bracelets of gold, Geneſ. 24. Therefore this it is wee teach for rules of Chriſtian ſobrietie, that if a woman ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede neither decencie in faſhion, nor the limits of her ſtate &amp; degree, and that ſhe bee proud of nothing, wee ſee no reaſon, but ſhe may weare any thing.</p>
            <p>It followeth: <hi>She is like a ſhip.</hi> But what ſhip? a ſhippe of Merchants; no doubt a great commendation. For the kingdome of heauen is like a Merchant, Mat. 13. and Merchants haue bin Princes, Eſay 23. and Princes are Gods, Pſal. 82. The Merchant is of all men the moſt laborious for his life, the moſt aduentrous in his labour, the moſt peaceable vpon the ſea, the moſt profitable to the land, yea the Merchant is the combination and vnion of lands and countries. <hi>She is like a ſhip of Merchants;</hi> there fore firſt to bee reckoned (as ye ſee) among the Laitie; not like a fiſhermans boate, not like S. <hi>Peters</hi> ſhip, for Chriſt did call no ſhe Apoſtles. Indeed it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable in a woman when ſhe is able by her wiſedome to inſtruct her children, and to giue at opportunities good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:133105:13"/> to her husband: but when women ſhall take vpon them (as many doe) to build Churches, and to chalke out diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline for the Church, this is neither com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dable nor tolerable, <hi>for</hi> her hands (ſaith <hi>Salomon) must handle the ſpindle,</hi> verſ. 19. the ſpindle or the cradle, but neither the Altar nor the Temple: for S. <hi>John</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth euen to the elect Ladie not ſo much her talking, as her walking in the commandements, 2. loh. 5. 6. Therfore to ſuch preaching women it may bee anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſometime anſwered the Image of the bleſſed Virgin at the great Church at Spire in Germany; <hi>Bernard</hi> was no ſooner come into the Church, but the Image ſtraight ſaluted him, and bad him, God morow <hi>Bernard.</hi> Whereat <hi>Bernard,</hi> well knowing the iugling of the Friers, made anſwere againe out of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> Oh (ſaith he) your Ladiſhip hath forgot your ſelfe, <hi>It is not lawfull for women to ſpeake in the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, the Merchant is a profitable ſhip, to teach a wife in all things to ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour her husbands profit: but many wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:133105:13"/> are like water-pageants, made onlie for ſhew, like pictures in a table, good for nothing but to pleaſe the eye, no longer to be liked than they be looked on, yea ſo vnproſitable and diſſolute in the houſe, as no man would thinke them to bee wiues, but that at meales he findes them ſitting at the vpper end of the table: whereas of the good wife it is ſaid heere, that <hi>ſhe will doe her huſband good, and not euill,</hi> verſ. 12.</p>
            <p>Again, the Merchant is a painfull ſhip, and ſhe muſt bee a painfull wife; not like a running pinnace to skoure from coaſt to coaſt, from houſe to houſe, as many A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenian women do, who giue themſelues to nothing, but idly &amp; wantonly to heare and tel newes; for he that hath ſuch a wife may thinke himſelfe married to an Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligencer; whereas S. <hi>Paul</hi> aduiſeth ſuch buſie bodies to gouerne their owne hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, 1. Tim. 5. as if intermedling with other mens did make them idle in their owne.</p>
            <p>Againe, being like a Merchants ſhip, that is, hee being the Merchant and ſhee the ſhip, ſhe muſt needs conclude ſhe was made for him, and therfore a ſhip of traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:133105:14"/> to enrich him, but not a pirate to ſpoile and rob him. To ſpoile and rob? as if a woman could robbe her husband? Indeede it hath oſt been held a queſtion diſputable, though I in truth haue little minde to diſpute it; yet I heare what is ſaid to that purpoſe from the mouth of <hi>Eue, VVe eate of the fruite of the trees of the garden,</hi> geneſ. 3. <hi>VVe,</hi> therefore ſhe puts in her ſelfe; and ſhe eates <hi>of the trees</hi> indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely, therfore of all the trees in the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and therefore all was hers as well as <hi>Adams,</hi> and the womans in right as well as the mans. To which I anſwere, that all is hers in participation to vſe, but <hi>Adams</hi> onely in diſcretion to diſpoſe, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by two reaſons, firſt, becauſe the beaſts were named by <hi>Adam</hi> and not by <hi>Eue,</hi> and to name is a note of dominion and authoritie: as when <hi>Joſeph</hi> became <hi>Pharaohs</hi> ſeruant, and <hi>Daniel</hi> a captiue to the Chaldeans, they receiued from them other names; and we in our baptiſme re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue our names to acknowledge that we belong in right to Chriſt. Secondly, the whole world was giuen to <hi>Adam</hi> before
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:133105:14"/> 
               <hi>Eue</hi> was made, ſo as hers was but an after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, and if ſhe haue any tenure at all, ſhe holds <hi>in Capite,</hi> &amp; ſhe hath no title but by her husband: ſhe therefore that vſurpeth abſolute authoritie in the houſe, is no Merchant, but a pirate to the Merchant.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, ſhe is like a Merchants ſhip, that is, a friendly fellow and peaceable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion to him, but not a man of warre to contend with him. For he that made her neuer built her for battaile ſure; ſhe was built for peace, and not for warre, for Merchants weepe to thinke of warre: therefore ſhe muſt not for euery angrie word of her husband betake her ſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the gunne-roome ftraight and there to thunder, to charge &amp; diſcharge vpon him with broad words, or as marriners ſay at ſea, to turne the broad ſide; like <hi>Zippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> the wife of <hi>Moſes,</hi> to raile vpon him, <hi>Thou art indeede a bloudie huſband,</hi> Exod. 4. this is no ſhippe of Merchants, this is the <hi>Spite,</hi> I thinke: and therfore no marucile, if many men thus ſhipt doe wiſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues a ſhore, and that vntimelie death might take ſuch a wife for a prize. When
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:133105:15"/> 
               <hi>Eliezer</hi> went a wooing for <hi>Iſaac</hi> his maſters ſonne, the triall by which he propoſed to prooue a fit wife for <hi>Jſaac</hi> was this, <hi>that if</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>when I ſay to a maide, Giue mee drinke, ſhe ſay againe, Drinke, and I will giue thy Camels alſo,</hi> ſhee without more adoe ſhould bee a wife for <hi>Iſaac,</hi> Geneſ. 24. that is, as <hi>Theodoret</hi> expoundeth it, If ſhee were gentle; not like that woman Ioh. 4. Chriſt asked her water and ſhe called him Iew: <hi>How is it that thou a Jew askest water of me a Samaritane?</hi> For though there bee many ſinnes incident to women (as there bee (to ſpeake vnpartiallie) as many to men) yet no vice in a woman ſo vnwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manly as this; yet if <hi>Adam</hi> had been fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious the matter had been leſſe, for he was made of earth, the mother of iron and ſteele, the murthering mettals; but the woman ſhee that was made of ſo tender mettall to become ſo terrible, the weaker veſſell ſo ſtrong in paſſion, yea to looke ſo faire and ſpeake ſo foule, what a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarietie is this? There was great reaſon ſure to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare a good woman to a ſnaile, not onely for her ſilence and continuall
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:133105:15"/> keeping of her houſe, but alſo for a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable timorouſnes of her na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which at the leaſt ſhaking of the aire ſhrinks back into her ſhell; and ſo ought the wife to do, if her husband but ſpeak to play all hid and vnder hatches, and to put out a flag of truce as <hi>Abigail</hi> did to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> and to ſay to her husband, as <hi>Rachel</hi> to her father, <hi>Let not my Lord be angrie,</hi> Gen. 31. <hi>Like a lilie among thornes</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon) ſo is my loue among the daughters,</hi> Cantic. 2. Like a lilie firſt, not like a nettle: againe, like a lilie among thornes, as ſhewing pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience in the ſoreſt pouocation. <hi>Sara</hi> indeede was peaceable, and ſo were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more, yet their praiſe was leſſe, in as much as they had meeke husbands, for ſhe is a monſter that liueth not meekly with a meek husband, but ſhe that is yoakt with a <hi>Nabal,</hi> a churle, a foole, as <hi>Abigail</hi> was, and beares that patiently, ſhee may ſay with <hi>Deborah,</hi> in the fifth of the Iudges, <hi>O my ſoule thou hast marched <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aliantly:</hi> And there ſhall more true honor grow to you by ſuch patience, than if ſouldierlike yee did preuaile by furie &amp; violence; and the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:133105:16"/> worſe your husbands bee, the more ſhall your vertue ſhine, which in affliction ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth moſt, like ſtarres twinckling in the night; &amp; if it be grieuous to finde matter of patience there where ye lookt for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and protection, yet it ſhall haue in tho end a reward, and in the <hi>Interim</hi> a ſingular admiration, and, as <hi>Mary</hi> ſaith of her ſelf, <hi>All generations ſhall call ſuch bleſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It followeth in the text: <hi>She bringeth her ſood from a farre.</hi> As ye haue heard what ſhe is like, ſo now likewiſe what ſhe doth too; for being is knowne by doing, as the tree is knowne by the fruite. Alas it is a ſmall thing, yea it is nothing to bee like, for copper oft times is like good coyne, and the diuell is like an angel of light, and if euill women were not like to many things, which indeede they are not, they could not deceiue ſo many as they doe: therefore the next thing is to conſider what ſhe doth; <hi>She bringeth her foode from a farre. she bringeth,</hi> firſt, therefore deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed <hi>pacie aduer ſa non auerſa,</hi> with her face, not with her backe toward: for when a ſhip goeth foorth, euery man murmureth
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:133105:16"/> for that it carrieth, the Merchant himſelfe feareth leſt it miſcarrie; but when it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth, there is ioy for that it bringeth. And where <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith <hi>ſhe bringeth,</hi> hee meaneth not that ſhee bringeth in with her, as if a wife were to bee choſen by her dowrie; for the worſt wiues haue many times the beſt portions, and the beſt wiues (ſuch as <hi>Ester</hi> was) haue oft times none at all. Indeede the manner of the world is now to ſeeke wiues, as <hi>Judas</hi> betrayed <hi>Christ,</hi> with <hi>Quantum dabis,</hi> What will yee giue? and if the father chance to ſay with Peter, <hi>Aurum &amp; argentum non est mihi;</hi> let her the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be as obedient as <hi>Sarah,</hi> as deuout as <hi>Anna,</hi> as vertuous as the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> yetal this is nothing, <hi>Quaerenda pecunia pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mùm est,</hi> other things may mend it, but monie makes the match. Therefore this was not it which <hi>Salomon</hi> meant by bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: for a good wife though ſhe bring in nothing with her, yet through her wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and diligence great things come in by her; ſhe brings in with her hands, for <hi>ſhe putteth her hands to the wheele</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) verſ. 19. and indeed if her worke
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:133105:17"/> doe not counteruaile her meate, then is euery finger of her hand like a theeſe in the houſe. Againe, if ſhe be too high to ſtaine her hands with bodily labour, yet ſhe bringeth in with her eye, for <hi>ſhe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeth the waies of her houſehold</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon) and eateth not the bread of idlenes,</hi> verſ. 27. Againe ſhe bringeth in by her fruga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, for ſhe holdeth it a point of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, neither to fare more daintily, nor to attire her ſelf more trimly, than may ſtand with her husbands ſtate: for if ſhee waſte more than ſhe bring in, &amp; her victualling amount to more than her whole voiage, that Merchant was ill aduiſed that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned her foorth, and it had been good for him to be alone. But as the ſaying is, that many men marrie their executors; ſo is it true likewiſe, that many men marrie their executioners: and as the ſinne of <hi>Adam</hi> began at <hi>Eue,</hi> ſo the ruine and confuſion, the extortion, oppreſſion, griping of te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, yea and ſacriledge of many men beginneth at the pride of the woman; for now euerie Ladie of the lateſt edition if her husband haue bribed out but an end
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:133105:17"/> of an office, yet ſhe reuels &amp; playes <hi>Rex,</hi> and ſhe muſt haue her Coach, though but to croſſe from the Church-ſtile to the Church-porch: and whereas thoſe Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiſh women, Exod. 38. when the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Tabernacle were to bee made, gaue in their deuotion their very Looking-glaſſes toward it; yet now the forbidden apple is pulled, the Church is robbed and ſpoiled, a Patrone will ſcarſe paſſe away a poore Parſonage, but with a reſeruation of his owne tithes, and all to maintaine French Hoods, Ruffes, Lawnes and Looking glaſſes: whereas of the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous wife it is ſaid verſ. 11. of the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that <hi>her huſband ſhall have no neede of ſpoile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what bringeth ſhe in? <hi>She brings in foode;</hi> in which word <hi>Salomon</hi> pointeth her out a houſeworke, as ſhe is a houſewife, and the worke aſſigned is the feeding of the houſehold: for wee reade that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> fetcht a calfe from the field, but <hi>Sarah</hi> had her charge to dreſſe it in the Tent, Genef. 18. and <hi>Samuel</hi> telleth the people, that their King when they had him, would
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:133105:18"/> take not their ſonnes, but their daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and make them Cookes and Bakers, 1. Sam. 8. and in the fifteenth verſe of this Chapter it is ſaid directly, that <hi>ſhee giueth the portion to her houſehold, and the ordinarie to her maides.</hi> But that which we reade <hi>food,</hi> ſome tranſlate it <hi>bread,</hi> ſhe bringeth her <hi>bread;</hi> and it may well be, for bread is the ſtaffe of life, and when like Merchants we haue runne round about the world to fetch in the riches of euery countrie, yet all is but to clothe the backe and feed the bellie: therefore <hi>hauing foode and raiment,</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>let vs there with bee content:</hi> 1. Tim. 6.</p>
            <p>Againe, as he is not the beſt Merchant to the Common-wealth which bringeth in toyes and trifles, but he which bringeth in ſuch things as beſt may ſerue neceſſitie; ſo neither is ſhee alwaies the beſt wife which is moſt adorned with trickes and qualities, but ſhe that endeuoureth moſt to that which is moſt neceſſarie. And I thinke ſurely that bread is expreſſelie na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med here, as to frame her whole conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, ſo chiefly her mouth with ſobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:133105:18"/> for many women are of the minde of the Iſraelites in Egypt, <hi>Manna</hi> is no meate with them, but they muſt haue <hi>Quatles,</hi> and all muſt bee daintie, (though to the vndoing of all) like <hi>Eue</hi> the wife of <hi>Adam,</hi> whom of all the trees in Paradiſe none might ſerue, but that which was the bane of her husband, and the leſſe they want, the more wanton and daintie mouthed they be. Now ſure if <hi>Cyrus</hi> had had ſuch a wife hee muſt needes haue worſhipt her, for he had no other reaſon to worſhip the Idoll <hi>Bell,</hi> but only becauſe it ſpent him ſo many ſheep, ſo many meaſures of flower, and ſo many pots of wine euery day: but euerie meate was not made for euerie mouth; only bread was made for all; and neither man nor woman haue warrant to aske for more than for their daily bread.</p>
            <p>But what meaneth <hi>Salomon</hi> by that, <hi>From a farre, ſhe bringeth her ſoode from a farre?</hi> Surely not to anſwere that which is Prouerbially ſaid, That farre fetcht and deare bought is fitteſt for Ladies, as now adaies what groweth at home is baſe and homely, &amp; what euery one eates is meate
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:133105:19"/> for dogs, and wee muſt haue bread from one countrie, and drinke from another, and wee muſt haue meate from Spaine, and ſauce out of Italy: and if wee weare any thing, it muſt bee pure Venetian, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, or Barbarian; but the faſhion of all muſt bee French: and as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith in another caſe, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icti <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictoribus leges dede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt,</hi> we giue them the ſoile, and yet they muſt giue vs the faſhion. Therefore this was not <hi>Salomons</hi> meaning, but <hi>from a farre</hi> either hath reſpect to the time, <hi>A longinquo tempore,</hi> as it ſeemeth to be expounded in the verie next words, <hi>She riſeth while it is yet night, and giueth the portion to her houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,</hi> &amp;c. He doth not ſay, ſhee meeteth it at the doore, as ſhee that riſeth to dinner, and then thinkes her daies worke halfe done, and for euery ſit of an idle feuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes her ſtraight to her cabbin againe, and if her finger but ake, ſhee muſt haue one ſtand by to feede her with a ſpoone: This is no ſhippe of Merchants, this is the <hi>Mary Slug;</hi> but <hi>ſhe bringeth it from a farre,</hi> that is, ſhee taketh care of it, and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth of it from the firſt, yea and before
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:133105:19"/> the firſt hand that toucheth it.</p>
            <p>Or elſe I take this <hi>from a farre</hi> to be far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet, euen <hi>ab vltimis naturae,</hi> from the firſt and furtheſt principles of nature. As for example, If ſhee will haue bread, ſhee muſt not alwaies buy it, but ſhe muſt ſow it, and reape it, and grinde it, and as <hi>Sarah</hi> did, Gen. 18. ſhe muſt Kneade it and make it into bread. Or if ſhe will haue cloath, ſhe muſt not alwaies runne to the ſhop or to the skore, but ſhe begins at the ſeede, ſhe carrieth her ſeede to the ground, of the ground ſhee gathereth flax, of her flax ſhee ſpinneth a threed, of her threed ſhe weaueth cloath, and ſo ſhe comes by her coate: The verie words of <hi>Salomon</hi> verſ. 13. of the chapter, <hi>She ſeeketh wooll and flax, and laboureth cheerfully with her hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or elſe I take this <hi>from a farre</hi> to be far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet, euen from the gates of heauen, from whence by her deuotion and godlie conuerſation ſhee draweth downe the bleſſings of God vpon her houſe. The barren <hi>Rachel</hi> praied, and ſo did <hi>Anna</hi> too, and by their prayers obtained childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Lord. Now ſure if the prayer of a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:133105:20"/> woman were ſo powerfull, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the courſe of nature to deriue and fetch children from a barren wombe, how much more ſhall it command the meaner bleſſings on the houſe? And therefore as a wicked woman is a ſea of euils, ſo a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous woman is a heauen of beautie, and there is none ſo faire as ſhe that feareth God: nay what ſpeake we of beautie? <hi>for fauour is deceitfull, and beautie is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>anitie,</hi> verſ. 30. of the Chapter: and as the pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a ſhip by weather and by water is waſht away, ſo ſhall all carnall beautie by ſorow, age and ſicknes euen wither and waſte into wrinkles; but <hi>ſhe that feareth the Lord</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>ſhe ſhall bee praiſed.</hi> Praiſed? yea honoured and admired; The ſtarres in the night, the Sunne at noone day ſhall not ſhine ſo bright as ſhe: for hee that goes by her doore ſhall point at her, and hee that dwels by her ſhall enuie him that hath her; and cuery man ſhall ſay, Bleſſed be he the that made her, happie is he that begat her, renowned is ſhee that bare her, but moſt happie, renowned, and rich is he that hath her: and as euen now,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:133105:20"/> ſo I ſay againe, <hi>All generations ſhall call ſuch bleſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, to make vſe of this in ſeuerall <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Application to the King.</hi>
               </note> kindes; I moſt humbly beſeech your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty firſt to admit of a particular applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to your ſelfe. It is ſaid <hi>Matth. 12.</hi> that the Queene of the South came to heare the wiſedome of <hi>Salomon,</hi> but we may ſay conuerſiuely and truly, that the wiſdome of <hi>Salomon</hi> is come to the King of the North: for your Maieſtie is to vs indeede a royall Merchant, not only for the vnion of holy marriage, which yokes &amp; couples one ſex with another, but as Merchants doe by intercourſe of traffique, for knit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and combining one kingdome with another. And I will not ſay it is kingly, but diuine and heauenlie to vnite into one things of diuided nature: for thus did God create the world, firſt he made things, and then he matcht them; firſt he created, and then hee coupled them; of man and woman he made one in mariage, of body and ſoule hee made one man, of ſea and land hee made one earth, of heauen and earth he made one world; but then came
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:133105:21"/> the diuell vpon the ſtage, and his part was againe to diuide what God had vnited, firſt man from God, then man from man, and that diuerſly, firſt in the very bond of blood and kinred, <hi>Cain</hi> from <hi>Abel</hi> the brother from the brother; then diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht by religions, the ſonnes of God and the daughters of men; then diſperſed by their ſeuerall habitations, the Iles of the Gentiles, and the Tents of <hi>Sem,</hi> and then diſtracted &amp; torne into diuers king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, the kingdome of <hi>Judah,</hi> and the kingdome of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> therefore doubtleſſe a glorious worke it were of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> againe to make one kingdome: for if it be ſo gracious in Gods eies to doe right and iuſtice to a ſtranger, how much more to loue a ſtranger, but moſt of all to take away the name of a ſtranger? The King of Kings be Pilot of your ſhip, yea thrice bleſſed and happie be your Maieſties en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deuour therein.</p>
            <p>Ladies and Gentlewomen, I beſeech <note place="margin">Application to Ladies &amp; Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> you miſtake me not, and impute no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialitie to mee. If I haue ſaid anything ſharplie, yet know that I haue ſaid no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:133105:21"/> againſt the good, but all againſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euill women, yea nothing againſt the ſex, but all againſt the ſinnes of women. To which if any replie: And why not (I pray) aſwell againſt the ſinnes of men? I anſwer, that he which impoſeth ſo much vpon the weaker veſſell, importeth much more to the ſtronger. There is a dutie required of the parents to the childe, as well as of the child to the parents; yet the ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth expreſly to the childe, <hi>Honour thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother,</hi> but nothing to the pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rets, that they being in order of nature and in wiſedome ſuperiour, might ſuſpect their dutie to be written in themſelues.</p>
            <p>Againe (Right Honourable in both <note place="margin">Application to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried.</note> ſexes) The cauſe of this meeting, the ioy of this day, yea the myſterie and little image of this great intended Vnion, Let me be bold (I beſeech you) in termes of modeſtie to make applicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to you. You are here met to be matcht, that is, to bee married, and <hi>mariage</hi> (as the Apoſtle faith) <hi>is honourable in all,</hi> but thrice honourable in you, firſt honourable in the inſtitution as in all other: ſecondly in your perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:133105:22"/> being honourable aboue other, but thirdly in your countries the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable of all other: for ſimply to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ioynes ſex and ſex, to marrie at home ioynes houſe and houſe, but your mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage ioyneth land and land, earth and earth, onely Chriſt goes beyond it, who ioynes heauen and earth.</p>
            <p>Therefore firſt to you, the honourable <note place="margin">Application to the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome.</note> Merchant of this honourable ſhip; you haue heard what is ſaid, that mariage is a ſore aduenture, and therefore as mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners vpon the ſea in the day time look vp to the Sunne, and in the night to the Pole ſtarre, ſo looke you vp day and night to God, and God ſhall giue you good ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping therein. A married man (they ſay) hath the charge of three co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monwealths, for hee is a husband of a wife, a father of children, and a maſter of ſeruants, and he hath daily need of God who ſhould guide all theſe. Therefore firſt loue God, and to proue that loue, loue alſo her whom God hath giuen you: for if (as S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith) He <hi>that loueth not his brother, &amp;c.</hi> how much more, he that loueth not his wife whom
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:133105:22"/> he daily ſeeth, how ſhall hee loue GOD whom he neuer ſaw? and indeed there is no religion nor goodnes in that man that loueth not a faithfull and loyall wife. And ſay not you loue, vnleſſe you loue to the end; for <hi>much water cannot quench loue,</hi> Cantic. 8. <hi>for loue endureth all things, belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth all things, and ſuffereth all things:</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if there grow by the wife any cauſe of griefe, yet you muſt remember ſhee is the weaker veſſell; God therein exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth your wiſedome in reforming, and your patience in bearing it; and with whom will a man beare, if not with his owne wife? If at any time you haue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to exerciſe your authoritie yet you muſt remember, it is authoritie tempered with equalitie; the wife is therefore to be gouerned with loue, not ouerruled by tyrannie. And let all husbands know this for a rule all things, that the wife ſhall much better do her dutie to her husband, when the husband doth his owne dutie in example before.</p>
            <p>And let me ſpeake one word to you <note place="margin">Application to the Bride.</note> this honourable Ship; you are turned by
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:133105:23"/> Gods prouidence to the right of a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant ſtranger, yet herein happy, that you neede not as <hi>Pharaohs</hi> daughter to <hi>ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get either your owne people, or your fathers houſe.</hi> All the time of your life you haue bin gathering for this day, therfore learne to practiſe now, what you haue learned before, that is, to honour, to loue, and to obey, and then at laſt you ſhall come to rule: for a good wife by obeying of her husband rules him; but ſhe that obeyeth not is like the conſpiracy of <hi>Corah</hi> againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron.</hi> Beſides, remember your badge is not as of that ſhip Act. 28. not <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux,</hi> for I finde neither ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition nor idolatrie in any part of your familie, but I finde among other things <hi>a ſheafe of wheate</hi> and <hi>a handfull of wheate</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unanced vpon your ſterne, therefore doubtleſſe it will be expected that Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, peace and proſperitie come in with you I might referre you for paternes of true vertue, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſometime referred <hi>Timotly,</hi> to <hi>Lois</hi> and <hi>Eunica,</hi> a grandmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; a mother; and indeed this chapter of <hi>Salomon</hi> is entituled, <hi>The prophecy or leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:133105:23"/> which his mother taught him:</hi> and if you remember the many good leſſons your mother hath taught you, then ſhall I need to ſay no more, then ſhall you be like <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel</hi> and <hi>Leah,</hi> which twaine did build vp the houſe of Iſrael: then ſhall you bee a ſhip indeed, for you ſhall bring your ſelfe and your husband to the hauen, euen to that which Sea-men call <hi>Promontorium bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae ſpet,</hi> The hill or hauen of good hope, that is, to heauen; and when this mariage is diſlolued, you ſhall marrie at laſt with the Lambe. In the meane time <hi>doe worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Ephratah, and be famous in</hi> Brittanie, <hi>liue to a hundred, grow into thouſands, and your ſeede poſſeſſe the gate of his enemie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p> And God almightie who brought vs all hither by the inſtitution and helpe of holy marriage, hee bring vs at laſt to that happie and endleſſe ſocietie with his Son, to whom with the Father and the holy Ghoſt be aſcribed al praiſe, power and dominion now and for euer, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
